<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Erik's Cool Blog</title><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/feeds/security.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://crustyassembler.github.io/</id><updated>2016-11-07T08:04:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>2FA: What it is and why you (totally) need it</title><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/two-factor-auth.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-07T08:04:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-07T08:04:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Erik Kaighan</name></author><id>tag:crustyassembler.github.io,2016-11-07:two-factor-auth.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two factor authentication is a method of securing computer systems by
requiring any authorised user to provide two pieces of valid evidence
in order to be granted access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence required is generally defined as something the user knows
and something the user has. Or to put it more elegantly,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mattblaze/status/792443648520650752"&gt;Tweet of mattblaze/792443648520650752&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While two factor authentication can make it more difficult for an
attacker to access a computer system protected by two-factor
authentication without access to the additional credentials, it may be
possible for the attacker to harvest the required information via a
range of social engineering attacks, one example of which being
phishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sophisticated spear-phishing attack, it would be possible for an
attacker to harvest all of the required data, immediately utilising any
required 2FA credentials, granting them immediate access to the
compromised system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-factor authentication is also more susceptible to the loss of any
required authentication tokens, especially when they take a pysical
form, which is more likely to cause a legitimate user to be locked out
of their own online accounts or computer systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the shortcomings of the implementations of current 2FA systems I
generally avoid using it where I can. By utilising strong, unique
sets of data to register each individual online identity I control, I
severely limit the impact that the compromise of a single one of those
identities is likely to have on any other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst practicing good operational security can be a labourious task,
it is becoming incresingly pertinent for even the average person to
consider, as surveillence is more constant and relentless than ever
before, and is only going to continue getting worse, and as such it is
naive to think that enabling a two-factor authentication service
controlled by yet another third party will help to secure your data at
all and is why you generally won't find me singing its praises.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="Security"></category></entry></feed>