<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Erik loves ambiguity! 😂👌</title><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/feeds/software-development.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://crustyassembler.github.io/</id><updated>2016-11-04T10:17:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Project Roles &amp; Responsibilities</title><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/roles-and-responsibilities.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-04T10:17:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-04T10:17:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Erik Kaighan</name></author><id>tag:crustyassembler.github.io,2016-10-31:roles-and-responsibilities.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Documentation provided by my employer claims that successful projects
are delivered by a "One Team" approach, incorporating a DSDM-based
project management plan within the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roles defined in the project management plan are stated to be
flexible in the sense that they may be carried out either internally or
externally as appropriate. The roles, and consequently their associated
responsibilities may also be shared by multiple individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following project role diagram aims to illustrate the
relationships between individual roles and responsibilities documented
within the DSDM development lifecycle specification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Diagram illustrating the DSDM Team model" src="https://crustyassembler.github.io/images/7a - The DSDM Team model.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is stated that a project is goverened by the head, which generally
includes the roles of business/project sponsor, improvement champion,
project manager and technical co-ordinator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The various roles generally involved in the project board are
documented as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Business Sponsor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Business Sponsor is the person or entity responsible for providing
the funding necessary for any concieved project to be seen through and
is as such ultimately accountable for the realisation of that proposed
project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Providing any support necessary for the project team
to successfully complete the project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Determination and production of the project's underlying development
architecture&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To govern any potential risks involved with the project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engage and govern the communication between the development team and
any project stakeholders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensure that the project stays aligned with the company roadmap
throughout its development lifecycle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Improvement Champion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Improvement Champion is responsible for the delivery of business
change and as a result directly supports the Business Sponsor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributing to key requirement, design and review sessions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling change management. Converting any project vision into a
working plan and directing the implementation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring collaboration between those responsible for fulfilling the
various management roles and any stakeholders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Providing the business vision definition for the project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling the approval of proposed changes in the requirements
definition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Manager&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project manager is responsible for the day-to-day running of the
project. The manager is accountable to the rest of the project board
and is expected to conduct regular project assessments and to report
any relevant findings to the project board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing project configuration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manage problems from the solutions development team as they emerge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintain communication with senior management and project governance
authorities throughout the project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintaining high level project and stage plans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resourcing specialists wherever necessary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technical Co-Ordinator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical co-ordinator is accountable for all technical solutions
design within the team. They are also responsible for ensuring that
the proposed solution is compliant with the design authority and any
other associated standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agreeing on and controlling the development of necessary technical
architecture&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advising on an co-ordinating the technical activities of each
involved team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identifying potential risks associated with any technical and
architectural design choices&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling technical aspects of transitioning the produced solution
into a live environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resolve technical differences between technical team members&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body of the DSDM project role diagram depicts all of the people or
entities pysically responsible for the production of the proposed
project and is actively directed by those responsible for fulfilling
the aforementioned management roles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Team Leader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team leader is a central role that aims to ensure that the delivery
team is working effectively and to communicate progress with project
governance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focusing the team to ensure appropriate and timely delivery of any
agreed solutions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To encourage participation and co-operation between team members to
ensure the best possible outcome for the project within any provided
boundaries&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that the iterative development process is adhered to by the
team at all times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To monitor the day-to-day development of the team itself through all
team activities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To organise and run team meetings as often as is necessary and in a
timely and focused manner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Business Ambassador&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business ambassador is a support role within the team that aims to
provide a business perspective for all decisions potentially related to
the solution's fitness for business purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The perspective provided by the business ambassador is generally
derived from that of any users of the produced solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Providing a business oriented view in all requirement, design and
review sessions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide a business perspective for all day-to-day project
decisions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Providing daily assurance that the project is evolving as it should
be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring the adequacy of any training carried out&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Communicating with, and involving users with the development process
as necessary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Business/Process Analyst&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business analyst aims to develop any project requirements, user
storyboards and benefits. They are intended to develop and design
business process improvement provisions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enforcing a high, timely standard of communication between between
business and technical participants in the project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing the design, development and distribution of all
products and documentation related to the project's business
requirement specifications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring that all of the implications of any day-to-day decisions
are taken into account&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Business Testers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Business testers aim to test the delivered solution based on any
requirements, either functional or otherwise. Ensuring that the project
meets the proposed standard and works as intended from the customer's
perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Service Managers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service manager is a role that aims to both run and improve the
delivered solution. All responsibilities involved with the operation of
the service are those of the service managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important that a service manager asks questions about any
relevant risks or fears that they may have that are associated with the
delivered product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Solution Developer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designs and develops the solution under guidance of the project's
technical co-ordinators. They interpret the project requirement
specification and translate it into a functional, working solution as
required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work with business roles and solution testers to iteratively
develop a functional, deployable solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Produce any plans required for the controlled and professional
development of the proposed solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To record and interpret any changes to the project requirements or
any information likely to impact the development process of the
solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Participating in the quality assurance work required to ensure that
the delivered product performs as it should&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test their own work prior to any independent testing process&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Service Transition Manager&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service transition manager is a role that aims to ensure the
effective transition from project to service and support. They ensure
that the service is ready for change, including any associated
documentation and training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Solution Tester&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solution testers ensure that the delivered solution meets all proposed
technical and functional requirements from a technical perspective. The
solution testers and fully integrated with the solution development
team and work closely to ensure that all technical requirements are met
either during or following development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work with business roles to define test cases for the solution as
it contines to evolve, ensuring that old features are continually
regression tested in addition to any newly developed ones&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To carry out all necessary technical testing of the solution and its
features&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep the team leader informed on the results of all testing as is
appropriate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating test products, such as plans, test cases and logs of any
past testing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assisting the business ambassadors and advisors to ensure that it is
possible for them to accurately validate whether or not the solution is
fit for purpose at any one moment in time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="Work"></category><category term="Software Development"></category></entry><entry><title>SDLC at Work</title><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/sdlc-at-work.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-19T10:22:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-19T10:22:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Erik Kaighan</name></author><id>tag:crustyassembler.github.io,2016-10-17:sdlc-at-work.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Any project which has been both conceived and approved in my workplace is subject to compliance with an in-house operating model which intends to ensure that all solutions developed in the workplace are done so in an efficient and professional manner. The operating model employs a combination of both iterative and incremental development principles and as such at regular intervals during the development of any solution, the needs of the customer are re-evaluated and if necessary a request for change can be made; potentially influencing the repetition of the entire process until the solution is deemed to be complete by the developing team, governance, testing, and the client. For this reason, I would liken the software development lifecycle implemented by my employer to the incremental lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cycle consists of (at minimum); the approval from Planning Lead based in part on a two-page opportunity statement, the creation and evaluation of a project proposal, and plan with complexity relative to its scope. Continuous development then follows; segmented with regular evaluations of project requirements, testing and the potential implementation of any significant requests for change approved by the change advisory board or smaller bug-fixes and minor feature implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opportunity statement when put most simply is a short statement underlying why a project or change is a good idea. This document is required to be sponsored by a service lead and accepted by the appropriate governance group in order for the change or service to be continue to be developed and potentially implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project proposal can possibly cover a range of topics, however usually takes the form of just two major points. The first; &lt;em&gt;identifying&lt;/em&gt; any &lt;em&gt;current problems&lt;/em&gt; that the proposed solution aims to address. Secondly, the document aims to describe how the solution would &lt;em&gt;rectify&lt;/em&gt; any &lt;em&gt;identified issues&lt;/em&gt; if implemented, and how the company could &lt;em&gt;benefit&lt;/em&gt; from the implementation &lt;em&gt;overall&lt;/em&gt;. As a part of this process, the proposal is analysed to determine whether or not it fits the company strategy and is an appropriate solution for the identified problem. Beyond this the opportunity statement aims to identify the opportunity itself, which involves breaking down any user requirements into a brief summary, identifying any improvements that could be made to an existing system, service, capability or process and documenting the outcome that the developing team hopes to achieve with their proposed solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the identification of an opportunity, key dates and the potential consequences of not meeting them are documented. Points such as compliance deadlines or the potential loss of custom are appropriate examples of what this would cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information such as an estimate of the likely required financial investement are also extremely important to cover in the opportunity statement as it is a factor that can easily influence any final decision. A start and end date are also expected to be provided, demonstrating the range in which the project would ideally be in production by. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statement is also expected to contain a brief summary of benefits expected to be introduced with the implementation of the finished solution which is expected to be accompanied with a statement underlining any support for the company strategy. This generally involves identifying which strategic objectives the proposed solution complies with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key benefits the solution would provide are also expected be covered in the project's opportunity statement, documenting how the system would be improved with the implementation of the solution. Generating additional income, improving the speed or reducing the operating cost of current systems, improving customer service or user experience and maintaining complience with current and future legislation are all possible benefits of any new solution. This also involves documenting who will benefit from the project and how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of any project is required to be measurable, and as such, it is also important to document how the success of a new project will be measured in the initial opportunity statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design authority exists to ensure that the appropriate technical approach is taken in order to solve any given issue when producing a project design specification as is required. The design authority has the authority to either approve or reject proposed designs based on whether or not the project design specification complies with any given standard or is deemed by them to be an appropriate solution for the task on hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it is determined through these rigorous processes that the project meets all proposed requirements, the project is deployed as is appropriate. This usually consists of first being implemented in a testing environment, which allows any involved customers to determine whether or not the solution is fit for their consumption and is free of any bugs that are likely to negatively impact their experience when employing the solution as appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following this often lengthy procedure, the entire process is reviewed, with all involved parties considering how the process could potentially be improved and which stages of development were handled effectively. Additionally, the benefits of the developed solution are evaluated, determining whether or not the project was a worthwhile investment of resources, and how the solution could be implemented in the most effective way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the implementation of a solution in accordance with the operating model, maintenance is delegated to a disparate team solely responsible for providing customer support for solutions previously implemented. When change is called for, control is passed back to the development team as is appropriate and the entire cycle is repeated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="Work"></category><category term="Software Development"></category></entry><entry><title>My Website Journey</title><link href="https://crustyassembler.github.io/neocities-rip.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Erik Kaighan</name></author><id>tag:crustyassembler.github.io,2016-10-05:neocities-rip.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I needed a template in order to accelerate the development process of a website I was required to produce under a relatively tight timescale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I opted to use my own work rather than that produced my someone else and as such my journey to duplicate and strip down a website of my own design began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step required duplicating the complete directory structure of the website, and populating it with the necessary files. Fortunately wget can be used to completely automate and simplify the entire process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;wget -rnH https://te1eph0ne.neocities.org
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point I had the entire directory structure at my fingertips and decided to fire up a web browser to test it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't overly satisfied with the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it didn't occur to me at this point to screenshot the incident, so I'll just describe it instead as I'm having trouble reverting the Git repository in order to resurrect the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What had essentially happened was that for some reason on my neocities site, I had prepended every path with a / which clearly denotes a file in the server's root directory, which was quite clearly incorrect in this instance and most others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fallout of this was the server being unable to locate various images, fonts, stylesheets and other necessary resources, causing the website to load quickly, but to be presented in an aesthetically incomplete manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then spent the required time rectifying the issue, and finally succeeded in both getting the resources to be referenced and served as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point it was simply a matter of fine-tuning the necessary elements, removing any unrequired DOM elements and populating the page with any relevant information and resources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</summary><category term="HTML"></category><category term="CSS"></category><category term="JavaScript"></category></entry></feed>